Right. Welcome along to the Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Committee again,
for our annual update on the Perceptions of Asia report.
Pleasure to have you with us. We're live streaming this, as usual, and we have half
an hour set down for this afternoon, so I'll hand straight over to you, Sue.
Amazing. Thanks, Chair. Really appreciate it.
Do we have our slides?
We do.
Amazing.
Ah, thank you.
Thank you very much.
So yeah, lovely to see you all. I know you're working
long hours at the moment, so really appreciate this 30-minute slot.
I'm also aware for a survey that was done at the start of
the year and released in June 2026,
that you may be familiar with the results already, but I hope this is
nonetheless just a useful refresher for you.
And we're very happy to answer any questions you might have
about the results.
What I'm going to do is pass to my colleague, Dr Julia McDonald.
She runs all of our experts dialogues across the
region, of which there
have been 20 in the past 25, 26
years, and runs the research program, of which this is the sort of
main centerpiece.
The Perceptions of Asia is a centerpiece of what
we produce as a
small sort of think tank like organization here in New Zealand.
This research generated 1.3
million impressions. It had over 12,000
readers. It's being used also not only here in New Zealand,
about how we think about ourselves and how we're looking at the region, but it's
increasingly informing
others who are looking at New Zealand and wanting to understand how we are relating
to the region. So we're seeing it being picked up and used for
comparative studies across globally now.
I'll pass to Julia, if you can bring-- How will we move slide to slide?
Yes.
Give you a-
Okay
... the eyebrows.
Sailing slide really. Slide!
Slide!
So, this slide gives you the background, but
it's in its 29th year, so it's a longitudinal study.
The main survey was carried out at the start of this year,
and the rest is fairly self-explanatory, but it takes in the
views of 2,300 New Zealanders
and is representative by age, gender, ethnicity, and region.
Right. Julia, all yours. Thank you.
Wonderful. Thank you, and thank you for the opportunity to present today.
I'm going to flick through a lot of slides, apologies.
I'll be saying slide a lot,
to give you the highlights of the data, and then we
can move swiftly into Q&A. Okay.
Sure.
Right. We can start on the next slide. Thank you.
So in terms of the big picture trends, New Zealanders are feeling more connected to
Asia in their daily lives than they ever have been before.
So this shows you that 60% of New Zealanders feel a medium to high
connection to Asia in their daily lives.
It's four percentage points up from the last survey.
If you want to know what's driving this sense of connections,
New Zealanders have a wide range of interests, but you can see here,
food and cuisine, New Zealanders love food from Asia, continues to be top of the
list, followed by tourism and travel, and then in a distant third place,
business and trade. We tracked where New Zealanders were going over the
last calendar year. Travel to Asia was up 14% last
year, with China, India, Indonesia, and Japan being the top
destinations for New Zealanders.
Next slide, please.
We did a separate research report earlier this year that looked at
Pacific New Zealanders' perceptions of Asia.
This gives you a sense of how different groups within New
Zealand are relating and engaging with Asia.
So you can see here that our Pacific New Zealand population is
more interested in Asian languages, cultural outputs, entertainment,
but also sports, and we see this correlate also with our Maori population, more
interested in culture, sports, entertainment, and also learning
Asian languages.
Next slide,
please.
K-pop.
K-pop. Korean was the top result by far. Yeah.
Really interesting.
A less positive trend has been the recall of Asia-related news.
So we started asking a question in 2010, "Do you recall seeing,
hearing, reading news about Asia in the past three months?" At that point in time,
70% of New Zealanders said that they could recall a news story.
This year, 35% say they can recall a news story.
So that's halving in a matter of 16 years.
If you flip to the next slide. One of the strongest hypotheses for this is how New
Zealanders are getting their news and the rise of social media as a primary news
source. You see 54% of New Zealanders say they get their
news from social media.
The gap between traditional media and social media was 10 percentage points last
year. That's a six percentage points gap this year.
We expect that trend line to continue converging.
We know that for the under 30s, 70% of New
Zealanders are getting their news primarily through social media.
So, a really important trend for us to be aware of in terms of getting news about
Asia out to the New Zealand population.
If you flip to the next slide, you might be wondering where.
What types of social media platforms are they getting their news from?
Facebook by far dominates, although that is driven by older New Zealanders
generally. Younger New Zealanders are getting their news from YouTube
increasingly, as well as Instagram, and then TikTok also on
the rise.
Turning to foreign policy, defence, and security.
We have asked since 2017 about friend and threat perceptions
in the region, looking at New Zealanders' views of different
countries. The macro trend this year is increasing
comfort with middle powers and growing
wariness with major powers. So here you can see Australia
tops the list in terms of close friends.
But if we zoom in on countries in Asia on the next slide,
you can see that Japan continues to top the list in terms of
closest friends in Asia,
followed closely by Singapore, then the Philippines and South Korea,
and those rankings remained unchanged from last year.
And if you go to the next slide, you'll see-
Sorry, can I ask you about-
Oh, yeah. Sorry.
I mean, you've highlighted that bit, but-
No, go back
... is there research behind that that says what is US and
what is just Donald Trump?
What we can see in a longitudinal trend line, so the United States
dropped 22 percentage points in the past year-
Yeah
... which would correlate with Donald Trump's presidency.
Mm.
So we know that a lot of the reactions are very-
Because, it's quite a good headline, but I'm not sure that deep
down it actually reflects probably Kiwis' views about,
I don't know, if World War III happens, would you rather have the US
next to you or,
Indonesia or South Africa? They're probably going to take the US.
Yeah. So,
next year we're planning to put the US in our defense and security partners list to
see where it still ranks in terms of other metrics.
Yeah.
So we don't include the US in a lot of our questions.
This is the one where it is included, so we can see the friend perceptions over
time. We do know it has dropped in the past year, but it will be interesting
to see if it rebounds next year and we can ask more questions about why.
We do ask trust and major powers. So, there are a range of questions, so
we tend to ask the same question from different angles that enables us to
sort of triangulate. But you're right, this is broad perceptions-
Yeah
... from streets of New Zealand.
But also, I see you've got friend, close friend. What was the other option?
Was it just nothing
or was it ambivalent versus don't
think of them as an enemy? Is there a stronger
polarized anti-China than there is anti-US?
Is it just people are-
We know with a bit more granularity at the trust level, so when we get to the trust
slide, I'll show you.
Sorry.
No, no, no.
Go on. No, no, it's fair to-
These are good questions.
But we do, this is a through to threat,
and friend is a continuum, so it's not just giving them a choice of
positive or a choice of negative.
Yeah. Gotcha.
So if we go to this, you can see, as we mentioned, the US has dropped a lot in the
last year, 22%. Slight warming towards China,
which means that for the first time China has been seen as a closer
friend to New Zealand than the United States.
If we look at threat perceptions, you can see North Korea, Russia, those were the
top two last year, continue to be the top two this year.
The US has increased in threat perceptions 18 percentage points, so it now comes
third. China has dropped down to fifth in this
ranking.
Next slide.
We did add a new question this year about perceptions of like-mindedness to see
where New Zealanders were feeling more comfortable, which countries they saw as
being similar in approach in engaging with the world.
You see Singapore, it's a quarter of New Zealanders identify Singapore as the most
like-minded, followed by a fifth identifying Japan,
and then other countries sort of distant.
That kind of made me think about why people thought we were-
So we didn't have a follow-up question this year, but we do know why people
think of countries as friends, for example.
So there's, with Japan, we know that being a democracy,
respect for human rights, we know that sort of positive attributes of the
people generally through people-to-people links plays a big role in how New
Zealanders view these countries.
And this is where we get to the trust questions.
So you can see here, again, increase in trust in a lot of countries
and especially middle powers. So Australia has gone up, Japan has gone up 8
percentage points and overtaken the United Kingdom for the first time this year.
Singapore joins this group for the first time and goes in quite high at
65%.
But if you work down the list to your point for the United States and
China,
you can see higher low trust in the United States than you do in
China, and a bigger neutral sort of response for China.
What date was this taken?
February. January, February this year.
So that was pre-
Pre around-
Pre the closer combination with Singapore as well.
Yeah.
And then Russia.
Russia.
New Zealanders are interested in cooperating with a range of countries in
defense and security issues. So Japan always ranks top again, and
Singapore is second, though a bit more of a distant second in this regard,
followed by South Korea. And then again, a slight increase in
interest in cooperation with China this year, which we
interpret as China being an important country in the region, perceived to be an
important country in the region with which we have to engage on a number of issues,
including defense and security.
So the US doesn't even feature-
So we don't have the US in this group.
So one of the additions that we are going to include next year is to ask-
The US.
So has Singapore just been added or are they only now featuring?
Not to this one, sorry, the previous one.
So, oh, no, sorry, Singapore has been added.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah. Added.
Added, sorry.
Added. Okay.
Yeah.
Very interesting as to what people perceive.
Yeah. Yeah, it is. And it is impressions, it
is
what's making headlines. So-
Yeah
... and it correlates to later in the survey you'll see knowledge levels,
but we'll let Julia keep-
No, no, no.
The reins.
It's all right. Please continue to ask questions as we go.
Yes. Sorry on that, Julia, can you just delve into that
question a bit more? Because I thought it was asking
who respondents-
Feel most comfortable with working alongside these-
No. So the wording is which Asian countries are New Zealand's most important
partners to work with.
To work with?
Yes.
Okay, so it's not just-
To work with for security.
They may rank high because they're an important consideration.
Yeah.
They rank high because we want to work with them as-
Yes, although I do think people read that question in different ways.
I think some people interpret it to be these are important countries that we need
to engage with, and I think some people see it as a partnership
question. So, there is a little bit, when I've asked people how
they read that question, there's different interpretations, so I think we have to
be a little bit careful on this one.
Okay.
I think there was also,
we were doing this survey at a time where the US was making a lot of
headlines.
Mm-hmm.
So there's a little bit of
China sort of rebounding and-
Mm-hmm
... putting China featuring in some of these stats,
more than perhaps what we would normally expect.
Yeah.
In terms of what New Zealanders are worried about, what keeps them up at night,
fake news and misinformation ranks top, over half of New Zealanders seeing it as a
high concern, followed by climate change, the rise of authoritarian
systems around the world, and cyber attacks, other countries.
Interesting to see that despite the turbulent international environment,
New Zealanders are slightly less concerned around a military conflict between major
powers in Asia. Also slightly less concerned around the security situation in the
Pacific, both down four percentage points this year.
And if you flip to the next slide, you can actually see how this compares
to across the Tasman. This is the Lowy Poll result that shows how Australians are
perceiving the world and their vital threats.
You see cyber attacks, they're slightly more concerned about cyber attacks, also a
severe downturn in the global economy,
but a military conflict always ranks much higher.
Concerns around a military conflict always ranks much higher amongst the Australian
public than it does here in New Zealand.
Can I ask a quick question?
Mm-hmm.
Is there a reason that you ask about right-wing extremism, not just
political
extremism? Because the UK, for example,
have identified as both being both
extreme left, extreme right as being a real problem.
Yeah, this is the legacy of having a longitudinal survey, so we've kept the
wording the same.
I was wondering if it was in-- Okay, yeah.
And, I know because I think I was head of research at that time.
Yeah.
We were using
like wording so that we could compare to Lowy.
Yeah.
So we were deliberately using identical terms so that
we had direct comparative data.
Yeah.
Black is good, not concerned. Red is concerned?
Yes. Sorry. Black is concerned. Yes.
Thanks.
Interesting.
So looking forward-
Can I quickly ask-
Oh, yeah
... do you ask them where they think the cyber attacks come from?
Because it's really interesting when you look at the other threats picture of what
they think.
No, but we could. We could do follow-up questions on this one.
We haven't done follow-up questions.
It'd just be really interesting.
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
Because if there is lots of concern, but then on the other concern
of where they think this is coming from.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, we actually haven't done the follow-up.
Just interesting.
Some of the questions we do follow-ups to get more granular detail on each year,
and so we could do that next year to find out more information.
So looking forward, 81% of New Zealanders
now see developing political, economic, and social ties with countries in
Asia as quite or very important. So that's up from 67% in
2019.
Mm-hmm.
So we've increased 14 percentage points in a matter of six
to seven years, which is quite significant.
Mm-hmm.
In terms of importance of world regions to New Zealand's future, Asia holds
steady as second only to Australia, which we sort of classify on its
own in the survey. The only two regions that really took a
significant dip this year was North America, down nine percentage points, and the
Middle East, down five percentage points.
We do look at the importance of sub-regions.
You can see here North Asia really quite significantly ahead of other
sub-regions in terms of perceived importance.
The powerhouses of China, South Korea, Japan, really driving that, as
well as increased entertainment
consumption amongst New Zealanders from that region.
You have Southeast Asia holding steady at 51%, and then South Asia
growing in importance, up four percentage points to almost on par now with
perceived importance of Southeast Asia.
Yeah, so that was just a few weeks after the FTA was signed.
It was, yes. Exactly. So there was a lot of news stories in December, and this was
January, February.
And then we zoom in one more level of analysis to look at the countries.
You see China
seen as significantly more important at the top
than Japan, it's 10 percentage points ahead.
But actually, if you look at the very important numbers, it's 20 percentage points
ahead.
Japan is 71%, and then India another 10 percentage points
behind that. So quite significant differences in those top three, and then
Singapore and South Korea are in their own sort of category.
Sorry, what's the gain for India? I just can't see it under the-
Oh, I can see it. I think it was 2%, but that is me
remembering a graph.
It is 2%.
It is 2%. There we go.
Thank you.
Next slide, please. And then we look at why these countries
are seen as important, and we pick the top three here just to show that New
Zealanders see them quite differently.
So five out of the top six responses for China are
all trade-related, really, and this was an open comment answer, so it was
coded after the fact.
With Japan, actually, technology and AI topped the charts, which was
surprising for us. But a sense that technology advancement really
matters, as well as tourism and travel coming in third.
For India, large population really matters, as well as immigration and those
people-to-people links, and then trade after that.
So you can see New Zealanders have quite nuanced views of how these countries are
seen as important to us.
In terms of knowledge, 58% of New Zealanders think they know at
least a fair amount about Asia. That's up from
33% in 2013, so a
significant rise, now almost the same or on par with South Pacific and
self-assessed knowledge of North America.
The interesting lags are in sub-regions.
So North Asia, New Zealanders feel very comfortable with, 54% say they know a
fair amount, 40% say they know a fair amount about Southeast
Asia, 29% say they know a fair amount
about South Asia, despite being seen as of growing importance.
Mm-hmm.
So that's where we see a real opportunity to grow-
Mm
... grow knowledge.
Last two slides, how New Zealanders think Asia will impact New Zealand's future.
Over 70% think investment from Asia, economic growth, tourism from Asia,
and technology and innovation in Asia will benefit New Zealand very positively.
Over half still see immigration from Asia to New Zealand as
positive. The political and security situation and environmental issues are the
two categories that people seem to mark as being of concern, and we're going
to dig a bit deeper into that in the next survey to ask what people are concerned
about specifically in those areas.
And then where do New Zealanders want to see more investment?
Science and technology, research and development, healthcare and biotechnology, and
infrastructure and transport were the top three that New Zealanders listed in
that question.
Great.
Yeah.
Thank you very much, Julia.
I thought just before opening up for questions, it might be useful
for you to hear the three or four things for
us as the agency that has led this research for the last 29 years, what stood
out for us.
I think the first was this, exactly as you note, Mr Costley, this was in
many ways a survey of President Trump.
He was very much dominating-
Yeah
... the headlines throughout the survey period.
And over that period, China was quite quiet, so it was very much Trump in the
headlines, so that really stood out for us,
and reinforces the point that we've long seen in the survey that New Zealanders
have always shown wariness towards two major powers.
So there has always been a correlation in this survey of
quite high-level wariness of major powers, nuclear powers, and
then real elasticity according to who's
president or what issues.
So missile tests, Wang Yi's visit to the Solomon Islands, any of those
types of things. Likewise, Gaza, Iran, that's
where we see really big movements, when normally what
is statistically significant in a survey of this size is plus or minus 2%.
So that's where we see those really significant shifts.
Second will be that the data shows that New Zealanders are actually really
connected to positive and interested in Asia.
They're more knowledgeable than they've ever been, and they're more aware that the
Asia region is giving us options. So we really see those three
middle powers, particularly Singapore, Korea, and Japan, come through again and
again as
trusted other powers in the region who
there's quite a high level of comfort with in terms of the permission space in
which you work with.
The third, in terms of engagement, you'll see trade
remains a really critical lens through which New Zealanders are
looking at the region and where there's a high level of comfort.
But for younger New Zealanders, that is less so.
For younger New Zealanders, it's a very broad association
with Asia,
but significant gaps of knowledge.
So Julia highlighted, for example, recognition that
India is 1.4 billion, is going to be consequential to our future,
but actually, when you look under the bonnet, low levels
of knowledge and familiarity there.
And lastly, I think this year's POA really tells a media
story. I think that shift in where New Zealanders are getting this news
from that is informing these perceptions.
We're seeing the role more and more played by social media
with the rise in AI, and
questions about how much we can verify the news and where we're getting
information from. You can see that's going to start to inform perceptions,
and obviously with
social media ban, it's interesting, and that might too where for
younger New Zealanders, this is their main source of Asia
news. So, that too is something to throw into the
mix. But I'll stop there and really happy to answer any questions you've got.
Thanks.
Excellent. Thanks, guys. All right, questions?
Yeah.
I just pulled out-
You begin.
Yeah.
Sorry. Damian, could I just pull one out here, the
2024 one. And you've done a regional survey of-
Yep
... knowledge.
Mm-hmm.
And so you've dropped in this time of y-
Yeah, I think we actually have a slide, a backup slide-
We do
... that shows the difference of knowledge over regions as well this year.
Just didn't want to go death by PowerPoint.
We tried to-
I g- yeah, I guess the
thing being, is it related to tourism simply, or is it related to other things?
Go ahead.
The difference in the knowledge about cities-
Yes
... versus-- Yeah, I think it's a mixture of things.
I think it's travel opportunities, but also-
Trade
... trade, connections to diaspora populations, food, connectivity, because
it's all about the different ways and different touch points to Asia, and there's
just a much wider variety of those in all of the big cities.
And I think we saw quite similar results where the areas that helped
guide our work were where we could see, a region for which
trade with Asia is really critical, but low levels of knowledge.
For us, that tells us we need to get, when we're bringing experts in from the
region, we can be line to that region and help share
expertise that gives a broader picture on why Asia's important and
views from the region. But certainly for urban capitals, that's where you
see high levels of knowledge and familiarity.
Interesting.
But I don't know, if you flick through the slides-
Okay
... beyond the questions slide.
Southland needs some education
That target was very high, actually.
Yeah.
In this, in the London-
South is not quite so.
Yeah.
Thank you. We've met before, and I really appreciated the long briefing.
One thing you mentioned when we met was the fact that there aren't foreign
correspondents-
Mm
... based in Asia, and I was wondering if you could just speak to that maybe
compared-
Sure
... to other regions. And the second thing, because I think Tim raised
a really good point about the Trump issue.
That graph is really interesting.
It almost looks like a whale on stage where it's the-
Oh, do you want to show the time trend? Sorry.
Yeah, the time trend.
It's right after-- It's-
If you go back one.
It's just after the question slide.
That one. There we go.
So this gives you the longitudinal data
that shows that shift. So the top blue is the United
States, and the bottom is China.
So in 2017-
62 and 63%.
Yeah. So close.
Fascinating.
Yeah.
And then you-- Yeah.
We all pretend to be surprised.
Yeah.
It does look like a whale.
Yeah, that was a good-
On the foreign correspondents-
Yeah
... New Zealand has no foreign correspondents based anywhere in Asia.
So generally, if there are reports coming out from New Zealand
media and on the ground, it's usually provided for
by us or also
building media familiarity in China is also supported by the New Zealand China
Council.
Mm.
But that too has an impact on what New Zealanders are seeing-
Exactly
... because they are largely reading
international news, if they're tuning into other
platforms that's produced for other countries.
So something that we at the foundation are doing are starting an
Asia headlines service, which will be weekly.
We're going to curate it for New Zealanders by us,
trusted news source. So really trying to build up to say, and we will
be doing that both in video and written form.
We will continue to build and train and provide opportunities for New Zealand
media so that they can access
on the ground because we notice a tremendous difference between
those who are reporting from New Zealand looking at an issue to those who
have had the opportunity to be there in person.
And just one other question was, does anyone do a
reciprocal data gathering exercise within Asia that includes New
Zealand perceptions?
Yeah,
Lowy does a power index. So that looks at soft
power ranking, military power, and so on.
And that public opinion poll includes New Zealand as well.
Okay.
Yeah.
We rank top of theirs as well.
But no one else outside-
Soft-
... Lowy.
Tourism New Zealand, I think, have traditionally done some of that stuff.
So what we have done, we did do a Southeast Asia perceptions of New
Zealand survey also this past year-
Yeah
... where we took four countries-
Four countries
... across Southeast Asia and asked how they viewed us, whether they
trusted us, did we stick to our word-
Mm
... where are we making the most impact, and so on.
And that survey came back unbelievably positive.
Mm.
Really a sense that New Zealand was a valued partner in the region.
Highly trusted.
One of the messages that was interesting for us was that sense that they really
wanted us to be
a voice for democracy and rights in the region-
Rule of law
... which I think is also responding to rising authoritarianism in
general. So that still,
where they may not be able to always be that voice, they still see the value
in other friendly countries. I think Europe
also has similar stats where-
We're hoping to do a similar survey with South Asia views of New Zealand-
Wow. Fantastic
... over the next year, to flip the switch, to get a sense of-
Exactly
... how we're doing-
That's right
... in other people's eyes. Yeah.
Yeah. But we do, because of the way we
word some of the questions, we can compare to Southeast Asia, we can compare to
Australia. India's really hard to survey in, but we
try and make sure it's always got that comparative data and comparative value.
Yes.
Do you do any sort of updates through the year or when key
issues come along or? Because obviously, the timing of the
survey-
Yes. In fact, over the next week, I'm hoping to start drafting questions for
a mini poll. So we do mini polls regularly.
Yeah.
We did one before the last survey because the gap between the survey taking and
the survey release was so big in terms of events in the world.
So we did a-
Yes
... mini poll right before the last one.
This time, we shrunk the timeline so that we didn't have that gap.
But we're going to keep doing mini polls to be a bit more responsive to events
in the world and to get sort of accurate data over the year, so
we can track New Zealanders' views and response to the events that are happening.
So I suspect a lot of respondents would
focus on what their view at that time and-
Yeah. Absolutely
... not necessarily recall things that happened over the past five months.
Yeah. We often show a timeline of events to show what was
impacting New Zealanders at the time of the survey.
Like firing tests or ballistic missile tests-
Exactly. Yeah
... or sorts of things that-
It's also why the longitudinal data is so important, because you see these
spikes in response to events, but actually, it's the long-term trends that are the
most useful.
Yeah. And the only other slide I thought it might be worth showing is the one
on perceptions of political influence in the Pacific.
Ah, yes.
I don't know if you've got that one.
We do have that one.
Yeah.
There we go.
Ah, there you go. Yes.
Just because it struck me as
quite different in terms of the reality of Australia's contribution to the Pacific
compared to New Zealand's, for example.
Yeah. It was very interesting. These were two new questions.
This year, we looked at political influence and developmental contributions, the
Pacific and perceptions of that among New Zealanders.
These were the only countries listed, so the
respondents could only choose from these countries.
But you see a perception that New Zealand and China were the most politically
influential, with Australia behind that.
Mm.
And then in terms of development partners, New Zealand and Australia were seen as
top, but New Zealand more influential than Australia.
And then China and the Netherlands-
Japan.
Yes, Japan.
Oh, Japan?
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
Which actually has-
Which actually has a significant-
A long history and significant role
Yeah. Yeah
I think.
So it's interesting to see what New Zealanders think versus-
Yeah
... sort of the reality of the data. Yeah. Mm.
Yeah. We
thought this would start a whole nother big conversation.
We've got for, what, 30 minutes. We-
I know right. Show too many slides, this is the problem.
Yes. All right. Very good.
I guess you use this as a KPI, don't you, for your own
organization?
Mm-hmm. A little bit, yeah. Knowledge levels are important for us.
Mm-hmm.
So part of our, if anyone is interested, the foundation of
The Glance and how we measure our impact, we do have that.
But,
at its way,
New Zealander's familiarity, we use it to guide where we're going,
either experiential work or the insights work we're providing.
We also, if we know that, for example, with cyber
maybe, and a matter of interest to New Zealand or for
our policy, then it's an area we can dig into-
Mm
... and provide some ancillary support to.
So if there was one kind of message for the Select Committee for a
government-
Yeah.
You know, what would it be to continue to build the
relationship?
Across Asia. Yeah. So for our organization, is we want to be
useful to you. That is,
so where we know if there are issues or particular angles
you're grappling with, we have this polling capability, we have this research
capability. It's only 1.5 FTE, but the people I do
are super, super capable, so that's for us.
I think for the organization focus on Asia, trade
is really important, but I think we still keep forgetting the people.
Mm.
So I think that would be one thing, is that it's in our interest.
When I'm in Asia and when we're in Asia, we keep hearing the, "Yes, this trade
relationship's important," but for all of these partners across the region,
they also really value and want to see these other strands to the
relationship. I think second is focus our effort.
I think we've signed a lot of comprehensive strategic partnerships and strategic
partnerships. We, and we see this in research often, are
perceived to wax and wane, so sign and then sort of ebb.
So,
we could spend a huge amount of time sort of out in a much tougher
region, fighting fires and trying to be all things to all people, so really
focusing our effort and knowing where our strategic interests align country
by country, and just focusing on those areas.
And what we hear in the region is our partners in Asia understand that.
They appreciate our size, our geographic distance.
They actually want us to be impactful, so.
Mm-hmm.
And I think third, the distance between New Zealand and Asia is shrinking
rapidly. Asia is right here, the issues are right here,
technology through communities and so on.
So
building that capability here so that we, through our
education sector, through the work we do, I would argue is becoming
more consequential, not less, because the challenges that the region is
throwing at us are growing. And so we're really wanting New Zealanders who
are able to sort of navigate that, take the opportunities, but also
navigate the challenges.
All right.
Thank you.
So there's Julie. Thank you very much for coming in.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.
Cheers.